A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5533
The collection consists of ca. 787 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was originally loaned to the University of Virginia Library Special Collections Department by Mrs. Page Kirk, Miss Olivia Taylor, and Miss Margaret Taylor, "Lochlyn," Charlottesville, Virginia, on January 29, 1957. Shares held by the Misses Margaret and Olivia Taylor were bequeathed to Special Collections on March 25, 1986. The share held by Mrs. Kirk's daughter, Mrs. Mary Mann Moyer, was given to Special Collections on January 5, 1987.
Biographical Information
Wilson Cary Nicholas (January 31, 1761-October 10, 1820) was an American politician who served in the U.S. Senate from 1799 to 1804 and was the Governor of Virginia 1814 to 1816. Nicholas was born in Williamsburg, Virginia where he attended the College of William and Mary. According to Nicholas's entry in the Biographical Directory of the United States Congress, he served in the American Revolutionary War as commander of George Washington's Life Guard until the unit disbanded in 1783. This appears to be an error: his entry in American National Biography states that "he commanded Virginia volunteer units from the fall of 1780 until the following fall, but there is no evidence that he was actually involved in battlefield action." He married Margaret Smith of Baltimore, Maryland, and settled at "Warren" in Albemarle County where he became a member of the Virginia House of Delegates 1784-1789 and a delegate to the ratifying convention of 1788 which approved the Federal Constitution.
Robert Carter Nicholas (1728-1780) was the nephew of Wilson Cary Nicholas and the son of Dr. George Nicholas and Elizabeth Carter Burwell Nicholas (widow of Nathaniel Burwell) of Williamsburg, Virginia. His father migrated to Virginia; his mother was the daughter of wealthy Virginia landowner, Robert "King" Carter of Corotoman. Born January 28, 1728/9, both parents were dead by 1734. He studied law at the College of William and Mary and practiced in the general court under the royal government. He served in the House of Burgesses, 1755-61 as the representative from York County, and from 1766-1775 as the representative of James City County, and was Treasurer for the colony of Virginia, 1766-1775. He was a member of the Virginia General Assembly from 1776 to 1778 and in 1779 was appointed to the high court of chancery. Nicholas married Anne Cary, daughter of Wilson Cary of Warwick County in 1751 and the couple had four daughters and six sons.
(Robert Carter Nicholas, Sr.. (2009, September 8) In Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia. Retrieved 13:10, October 15, 2009, from http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php? title=Robert_Carter_Nicholas,_Sr.&oldid=312497296
George Nicholas, born in Williamsburg about 1754, was the son of Robert Carter Nicholas, treasurer of Virginia from 1766 to 1776, and a great grandson of Robert "King" Carter. He attended the College of William and Mary and became a noted attorney. Nicholas was a lieutenant colonel in the Continental army but spent much of his time in Baltimore and did not participate in any significant engagements. During service in the House of Delegates in 1778-1779, 1781-1782, 1783, and from 1786 to 1788, the last three terms representing Albemarle County, Nicholas became friendly with James Madison. Elected to the Virginia Ratification Convention of 1788, Nicholas followed Madison's lead and spoke in favor of ratification of the proposed new Constitution. Soon after the convention, he moved west to Kentucky, where he had a distinguished career as an attorney, as a leading member of the Kentucky Constitutional Convention of 1792, and as the first attorney general of the state and professor of law at Transylvania University. Nicholas wrote important letters on western affairs to Madison and to Thomas Jefferson, which George Washington also read, and tried to convince the federal government to increase its military presence in the West to protect settlers from Indian incursions and to secure westerners' access to the Mississippi River. George Nicholas died in Lexington, Kentucky, on July 25, 1799. (Library of Virginia website: http://www.virginiamemory.com/online_classroom/shaping_the_constitution/people/george_nicholas
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill, (commonly called the Edgehill-Randolph Papers) and the Wilson Cary Nicholas papers, ca. 787 items (6 Hollinger boxes, 2.5 linear shelf feet), ca. 1765-1869, n.d. All items pertaining to Thomas Jefferson have been transferred to the Thomas Jefferson Papers and are described in the online Calendar of the Jefferson Papers of the University of Virginia: Multiple numbers. A search for "5533" should find all the Jefferson items formerly in this collection, almost 400 items.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series:
Series: I) Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers, Subseries A: Correspondence (Boxes 1-3); Subseries B: Financial, Legal, and Miscellaneous Papers (Boxes 3-4); and Subseries C: Militia Papers (Box 4); Series: II) Randolph Family Papers (Boxes 5-6) and Series: III) Drawings, Surveys, etc. (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box).
Contents List
- Series I: Wilson Cary Nicholas Papers
    Subseries A: Correspondence
    - 1769 July 08 John Norton [and Sons, Merchants of London], to Robert C. Nicholas, Treasurer for the colony of Virginia, 1766-1775, discusses the progress of Nicholas's various business and shipping endeavors. The post script touches on Nicholas's petition, regarding the repealing of taxes, to the King and the Ministry, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:1)
    - 1769 July 28 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, replies to Nicholas's offer to Norton of a shipment of tobacco. Also expresses Norton's sympathies in regard to taxation laws, which he believes that both the King and Parliament will work to revoke, 1 page (Box-folder 1:2)
    - 1769 August 18 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, apologizes for signing an address in support of the King and against those who believe in the Bill of Rights. Also thanks Nicholas for printing a cursory letter discussing merchant trade in Virginia, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:3)
    - 1770 January 03 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, acknowledges the letters that he has received and discusses the remittance of thirteen bills of Nicholas amounting to £2439.56, in past debts, 1 page (Box-folder 1:4)
    - 1770 January 24 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, confirms the transfer of money for 13 bills as described in Norton's last letter. Includes a receipt from John Hunter for 100 pounds due for an annuity, 1 page and a receipt (Box-folder 1:5)
    - 1770 March 30 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses the management of debts and other business. Refers to a proposal for use of copper coinage and notes that no further volumes are supposed to come out of Dr. Blackstone's commentaries and that he is now a judge, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:6)
    - 1770 April 21 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, deals with various accounts and bills for Nicholas who is shipping goods. Expresses sympathy with the colonies and explains that he had lived in Virginia in the past, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:7)
    - 1770 July 12 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses business and finance and includes his tobacco account, 1 page (tobacco account moved to the OS Edgehill-Randolph Box) (Box-folder 1:8)
    - 1770 July 28 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses drafts with Colonel Corbin for £591.12 and other business matters, 1 page (Box-folder 1:9)
    - 1770 August 25 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, acknowledges the process of two orders—one in regard to Portsmith and the other to Sarah Pitt for £260 and asks in future if he would indicate on each bill from which account it is to be paid, whether private or Treasury, 1 page (Box-folder 1:10)
    - 1770 December 01 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, requests payment for the shipping of garden seed (£8.2) Mentions the general belief that there will be a war with Spain. Includes an invoice and a bill of landing, 1 page, bill of landing and invoice slip (Box-folder 1:11)
    - 1771 February 13 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses Nicholas's continued business ventures; Refers to some British financial issue concerning Colonel Tucker and Mr. Hunter; Norton is having a new ship Virginia built at Ipswich; Explains that the possibility of war with Spain is diminishing yet he still hesitates to plan trips, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:12)
    - 1771 May 04 James Buchanan to Robert C. Nicholas, apologizes for his misplaced faith in Messrs. Dunmoor and for the delay in the transfer of the goods, 1 page (Box-folder 1:13)
    - 1771 May 29 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, refers to a previous letter from Nicholas that indicates that Norton has been acting as a financial agent for Virginia which no longer requires his aid. Norton suggests that for their occasional needs that they should use Mr. Montague, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:14)
    - 1771 July 18 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses business and the accounts concerning the poor cotton and tobacco crops, 1 page (Box-folder 1:15)
    - 1771 August 31 John Norton to [Robert C. Nicholas], has had a conference with Mr. Pownall concerning copper coinage which they feel should be at the Sterling rate, namely 46 half pence to the Avoirdupois pound, instead of 52 Irish currency, probably the Virginia halfpenny. Inquires after one J.N. who was ordered to leave Virginia for health reasons. Post script mentions that Mrs. Horrocks was suffering from a mild case of smallpox, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:16)
    - 1771 September 07 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses the shipping routes of various captains involved with various aspects of his business affairs. Assures him that Mrs. Horrocks is recovering fully from the smallpox, 1 page (Box-folder 1:17)
    - 1772 April 30 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, follows-up on business and private letters from March 31, 1 page (Box-folder 1:18)
    - 1772 May 15 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, states that there are two bills amounting to £ 151.18 enclosed; these bills are missing, 1 page (Box-folder 1:19)
    - 1772 July 09 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, discusses Nicholas's proposal to introduce copper coins and Lord Hillsborough's appreciation of the proposal and promise to speak with the King and Mr. [Charles Sloane] Cadogan, Master of the Mint. Discusses plans regarding the purchase of marble for a statue honoring Lord Botetourt (erected in Williamsburg in 1773) and the purchase of a clock for the new courthouse in Williamsburg, which will cost more than he has sent for the purchase. Advises Nicholas to discharge his bills and loans in London because of the financial crisis resulting from frequent bankruptcies among bankers and traders, not only in London, but also Edinburgh and Glasgow, partly caused by their tendency to gamble in Exchange Alley and partly by immense quantities of circulating paper, for which there is no real property, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:20)
    - 1772 August 08 John Norton to Robert C. Nicholas, provides additional news about the financial crisis in Great Britain, discusses payments made to Mr. Earnshaw, Duke of Beaufort, Colonel Corbin, Colonel Richard Randolph, and Robert Miller, mentions the work on the Botetourt statue, and informs him that Lord Hillsborough has gone out of office without completing the work for the copper coinage for Virginia, over his disgust concerning the desire for a new colony on the Mississippi. Also informs that Richard Oswald plans to lend money to Nicholas without interest, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:21)
    - 1783 November 24 A. Nicholas to John Richardson, discusses the conditions and requirements for hiring out his Negroes, expecting either a portion of the crop or the supply of their clothing and good food to the slaves and payment of the taxes levied upon them; he also discusses possible livestock deals, 1 page (Box-folder 1:22)
    - [ca. 1783] James Monroe to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses his plans to travel to the 'western country' and congratulates Wilson on his upcoming wedding; he also shares his plans of purchasing a tract of between six and ten thousand acres near Charlottesville, photocopy of 2 pages transferred to the vault, James Monroe papers (Box-folder 1:23)
    - 1784 June 07 Richard Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks his support for his claim for the loss of a shipment of flour for £466.18, which had been sent to Suffolk but stopped at Sandy Point by order of the Committee of Safety in 1776; Patrick Henry had told the House of Delegates to reject his claim because of the supposed poor quality of the flour, assuming it was like that of Colonel Sims who was refused at Williamsburg, but he offers the testimony of Committeemen Colonel Diggs and Tabb who had actually examined what he had sent, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:24)
    - 1788 March 08 George Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], gives brief news on the health of the receiver's wife and daughter and mentions a debt of his father's involving [John] Jacquelin Ambler, 1 page (Box-folder 1:25)
    - 1789 May 08 George Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, contains observations on his land in Kentucky, Mercer, Fayette, part of Lincoln, and the road from Limestone to Lexington. He has good prospects for crops of corn, tobacco, flax, and hemp and notes that "parties run high here. I absolutely refuse to have anything to do with politics," but is trying to put in motion something for the encouragement of home manufacturing. Urges his brother to purchase land but not to buy any until he has come and seen the country. George Nicholas's findings on his travels to several cities, 2 pages (26 1:26)
    - 1789 September 29 James Buchanan to Wilson Cary Nicholas, apologizes for missing Wilson and his wife before they leave the following morning, 1 page (Box-folder 1:27)
    - 1789 November 07 Samuel Smith to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses financial matters and the price of wheat and expresses regret over missing an appointment, 1 page (Box-folder 1:28)
    - 1789 November 24 George Nicholas to [Wilson Cary Nicholas ?], declares he will not accept the appointment from the President if it is an obstacle to anything he can make a profit from and will not accept a public office without a salary, 1 page (Box-folder 1:29)
    - 1789 December 03 Samuel and John Smith to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses the price of wheat and the government's need for it, 1 page (Box-folder 1:30)
    - 1790 Mar 24 Edm[und] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas?], discusses Randolph's concern with his current situation and past ill- successes. Despite these problems, he will stay one to two more years but asks the receiver to sell his Charlotte lands above White's Road. Provides information of his wife's critical situation, suspecting the loss of a fetus, 1 page (Box-folder 1:31)
    - 1791 March 06 Edm[und] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, has heard from [Littleton Waller] Tazewell and his destination is for the springs via Charlottesville, discusses political developments that are getting discussed more time in newspapers. Suggests that important changes to the constitution—extending its powers—are being discussed. Because of the sensitive nature of the material, Randolph suggests that Nicholas may learn more from Colonel Monroe who is carrying the letter, 1 page (Box-folder 1:32)
    - 1791 August 29 Sam[uel] [Dyer] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, requests payment of the £29 owed him by Nicholas, if possible, when he travels to Richmond, 1 page (Box-folder 1:33)
    - 1791 August 29 David Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, heading to the Prince Edward [County?] district court, discusses the terms of the payment of debt owed him and pledges the continuation of their friendship, 1 page (Box-folder 1:34)
    - 1791 September 07 Sam[uel] [Dyer?] to Wilson Cary Nicholas, expresses concern about testifying on his behalf in court in the dispute of Nicholas against his neighbor and hopes that can be avoided; he may not be able to attend the next District Court session at all because he will be in Richmond, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:35)
    - 1791 December 11 Edward Carter to Wilson [C. Nicholas?], short note promises his man Will to deliver two letters and twenty [guineas] for Mr. Cam[p]bell, the lawyer with whom Carter's son lives and asks for a sample of his flour, 1 page (Box-folder 1:36)
    - 1792 February 01 George Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a settlement with John Jacquelin Ambler and other business transactions and the acquisition of lands, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:37)
    - 1793 September 27 Carter Page to Wilson Cary Nicholas, expresses Page's acceptance of a request of Nicholas's because of the "high opinion that I have of your integrity…tho I don't know how I can justify it to Mr. Cary's Estate, for which I act,", 1 page (Box-folder 1:38)
    - 1793 November 30 Jacob Kinney to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the surveying of land in Montgomery County which has now became part of Wythe County, since Montgomery County was divided recently. Although the letter indicates that papers concerning this land were enclosed, these papers are not present. Gives Nicholas the ability to purchase land for him, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:39)
    - 1793 December 07 Edm[und] Randolph to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the hesitancies of banks and other financial offices to do much business after a "malignant fever" went through the town. Randolph, however, agrees to help Nicholas in his business endeavors which include a shipment of coal to Manchester and a promise to ship a stock of rods [for nails?] from Germantown if he approves, 1 page (Box-folder 1:40)
    - 1794 June 05 John Guerrant, Brigadier General, to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the sending of three copies of Militia Orders, on executive direction, he orders him to reclaim "such of the books containing the system of discipline published by Baron Steuben and adopted by Congress in their resolution of the 29 th of March 1779 as have been distributed among the former militia officers in your regiment" as well as those still serving and return them to him so they may be standardized according to the 22 nd Section of the militia law due to the threat to the country; he also states "The deranged state of the militia of Albemarle and Amherst, inconsequence of the delay in the recommendations of the off[icers?] 'till so late a period, had induced me to defer the regimental meetings of the commissioned officers for the purpose of being trained by the Brigade Inspector,", 2 pages (Box-folder 1:41)
    - 1794 August 23 John Guerrant, Brigadier General, to Wilson Cary Nicholas, sets the date of October 13 th and 14 th for the upcoming regimental meeting of the officers of the 47 th Regiment for training and instruction by the Brigade Inspector and October 15 th for a regimental muster, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:42)
    - 1794 September 05 John Guerrant, Brigadier General, to Wilson Cary Nicholas, encloses orders for the brigade (not present) stressing the need to complete their second detachment as soon as possible, informs him that the rendezvous point is to be Winchester, and describes the way he arrived at the different quotas for each regiment, 1 page (Box-folder 1:43)
    - 1794 September 06 John Richard, Jr. to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses a proposed purchase of 200,000 acres and then 400,000 acres. Asks Wilson to come to Richmond in the next ten days in order to sign the warrants and titles for the land, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:44)
    - 1794 September 06 George Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, cannot take the deposition of [James?] Breckinridge when Nicholas had planned due to the distance between Albemarle and Kentucky and discusses his concern over the seeming indifference of the government to the need for navigation and trade improvements on the frontier, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:45)
    - 1794 September 10 John Guerrant to Wilson Cary Nicholas, asks about his progress in completing his quota for the second detachment required from the third brigade as ordered by Major General Clarke and asks if he has any riflemen in the quota to have them bring their rifles or secure some, 1 page) (Box-folder 1:46)
    - 1794 September 11 James Breckinridge to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses the purchase of 500,000 acres of land from John Preston, "Smithfield," Montgomery County, Virginia, for £900. This agreement would be finalized in Richmond on September 9, 1797, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:47)
    - 1794 November 13 John Guerrant to Wilson Cary Nicholas, directs him to carry out the governor's orders concerning delinquencies in his regiment, 1 page (Box-folder 1:48)
    - 1794 December 24 John Guerrant to Wilson Cary Nicholas, indicates that Nicholas should give the enclosed lieutenant certificates to the most deserving officers, 1 page (Box-folder 1:49)
    - 1795 March 10 George Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, mentions an advantageous partnership concerning an iron works and discusses a small debt of £26, 1 page (Box-folder 1:50)
    - 1796 August 28 [Sarah Champe?] Carter, "Blenheim," to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], asks if the advice he has received about her daughter's fortunes is favorable, as she wishes the suit to begin as soon as possible since their brothers will never agree to let them have the interest of their fortunes until the suit is settled, 1 page (Box-folder 1:51)
    - 1797 August 29 George Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, Virginia, discusses the selling of George Nicholas's farm for £5000 and other business matters, 1 page (Box-folder 1:52)
    - 1797 October 19 John Lewis to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?], wants to know how soon he can pay a bond held by his father's estate as he needs the money for a land purchase, 1 page (Box-folder 1:53)
    - 1798 December 11 John Nicholas to Wilson Cary Nicholas, discusses relations between the United States and France, the anger of the state of Massachusetts which was very upset at the expenses of the government and the taxes which they had paid, the activities of [Dr. George?] Logan, a Philadelphia Quaker, a doctor, and a Republican who traveled unofficially to France to settle the differences between the French Directory and the United States government, and the need for good public agents in France. At the end, he mentions that the price of tobacco has increased to ten dollars, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:54)
    - 1798 Wilson Cary Nicholas to J[ohn?] Marshall, who in 1798 served as one of three U.S. ministers to France under John Adams, draft, expresses his admiration for Marshall in spite of their difference of political opinion, agrees that there is sufficient reason to go to war with France, but is afraid that commerce will be adversely affected by it, tries to correct misconceptions about his own viewpoint, and congratulates him upon his return home, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:55)
    - 1799 February 08 Ben Johnson to Colonel [Wilson C.] Nicholas, inquires briefly about payment of seven hundred dollars due today, 1 page (Box-folder 1:56)
    - 1799 July 17 Sam Coleman to Wilson Cary Nicholas, encloses and re- emphasizes an earlier letter, July 10, 1798, requiring Nicholas to appoint an inspector for his regiment's arms and to report on the condition of those arms, two letters, 1 page each (Box-folder 1:57)